A Guide to the Charles Olson Research Collection 1969.0001
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
- Series V: Photographs
  - F. Gloucester
    - Gloucester scenes, ca. 1920-1960; includes Oceanwood Cottage, Little Theater, etc., undated (Box 329:147)
      - Gloucester Harbor, December 1963, 1 photographic print; 9 x 12 1/4 cm (Box 329:147)
      - Early Gloucester, Stage Fort, n.d.; 1 photographic print; 8 1/4 x 6 1/4 cm (Box 329:147)
      - Fresh Water Cove, Gloucester Mass, 1930; 1 photographic print; 7 x 11 1/2 cm (Box 329:147)
      - Little Theter Gloucester Mass, 1929; 1 photographic print; 7 x 11 cm (Box 329:147)
      - Oceanwood Cottage, n.d.; 1 photographic print; 7 x 11 cm (Box 329:147)
      - Remi OBrien, Friend of the felte[?]r Cassear, 1 photographic print; 11 1/4 x 7 cm (Box 329:147)
      - Remi OBrien looking me over., 1930; 1 photographic print; 11 1/2 x 7 cm (Box 329:147)
      - Albert Alcaly Gregory Smith, n.d.; 1 photographic print; 19 x 23 1/4 cm (Box 329:147)
    - Gloucester scenes by Barry Paine. 8 prints., ca. 1968-69. (Box 329:148)
    - 28 Fort Square: interior of Olson's house, showing maps and notes on walls, writing on window frames., March 1970.; 48 prints. (Box 329:148a)
      Photographs by George Butterick; his gift to the Archives.
    - Photograph of Charles Olson. Typescript on mattboard reads "property of Vincent Ferrini, Gloucester MA." Charles Olson manuscript on verso, entitled "A Statement on the Sporn Case and on the Feinberg Law." (Box OS1:1)
    - Photograph of Gloucester MA vessel, the Elizabeth Howard. Manuscript on verso reads "Elizabeth Howard coming into Gloucester Harbor." Photographer's imprint reads "From Keystone View Co. Inc. 258 Washington Street.", 1928. (Box OS1:2)
    - Photograph of the ship "Mabel Leighton" at a rigging loft in Gloucester MA. (Box OS1:3)
    - Photograph of audience watching dance performance in a park. Taken from set of Olson family photos., ca. 1920's. (Box OS1:4)
    - Photograph marked "Annual Outing, City Employees, Aug. 20, 1925, Gloucester [MA]." Taken from set of Olson family photos., August 20, 1925. (Box OS1:5)
    - Photograph of Robert Creeley. Manuscript on verso reads "Photo, RC [Robert Creeley]/ Bana/ Mar 53 -, for Charles and Con August 54 Jon X W - [Jonathan Williams?].", March 1953. (Box OS1:6)
    - Photograph marked "First Mid-Winter -- of the Barrett Camp Association, American House, Boston.", February 10, 1923. (Box OS1:7)
    - Photograph of Committee on Street Railways, Massachusetts Legislature., 1908. (Box OS1:8)
    - Group photograph on steps of building., ca. 1920's-1930's. (Box OS1:9)
    - Photographs of drawings of Gloucester MA. Views of the city from the Harbor. 7 prints. (Box OS1:10)
    - Photographs of paintings of Gloucester MA. Views of the Harbor. 3 prints. (Box OS1:11)
    - Photographs of drawings of Gloucester MA. Views of the coastline. 6 prints. (Box OS1:12)
    - Photographs of paintings of Gloucester MA. Views of the Harbor. 5 prints. (Box OS1:13)
    - Photographs of paintings of Gloucester MA. Views of buildings. 5 prints. (Box OS1:14)
  - G. Miscellaneous Photographs Owned by Charles Olson (Not Family)
    - Photograph of the Eaton portrait of Herman Melville., undated; Presentation inscription on verso from Eleanor Metcalf. (Box 329:149)
      - To Charles P. Olson jr- This photograph of Eaton's portrait of Herman Mellville, from his ... daughter..., n.d.; 1 photographic print; 22 1/4 x 17 3/4 cm (Box 329:149)
    - Birthplace of Ezra Pound, Hailey, Idaho., undated (Box 329:150)
      - Birthplace of Ezra Pound, Hailey Idaho, 1 photographic print; 8 1/4 x 11 1/2 cm (Box 329:150)
    - Yucatan scenes., undated; 2 prints. (Box 329:151)
      - Villa Alcanich del Estado de Yucatan, n.d.; 1 photographic print; 8 x 11 1/2 cm (Box 329:151)
      - House at Lerma, 1950-1951; 1 photographic print; 10 x 17 cm (Box 329:151)
    - Photographs by Nicholas Dean (studies of seaweed). 4 prints., undated (Box 329:152)
    - Photographs by Dick Lebowitz., undated; 13 prints. (Box 329:153)
    - Photographs by Dick Lebowitz, n.d. (Box 329:154)
    - Photographs of Indian artifacts by Diana Woelffer., undated; 7 prints. (Box 329:155)
      - By Diana Woelffer, n.d.; 1 photographic print; 9 1/4 x 23 1/4 cm (Box 329:155)
      - This was found ... [?] illegible handwritting, 1 photographic print; 12 3/4 x 25 1/4 cm (Box 329:155)
      - Olmec[?] from a small village near Lerma, n.d.; 1 photographic print; 14 x 16 1/4 cm (Box 329:155)
      - This is a rare 4 legged bowe ..., n.d.; 1 photographic print; 15 3/4 x 21 1/2 cm (Box 329:155)
      - N.W. [illegible name], a beautiful ... wooden mask... [illegible], n.d.; 1 photographic print; 25 1/2 x 20 cm (Box 329:155)
      - Diana Woelffer, n.d.; 1 photographic print; 20 1/2 x 25 cm (Box 329:155)
      - By: Diana Woelffer, n.d.; 1 photographic print 20 1/2 x 25 cm (Box 329:155)
    - 19th- and 20th-century photographs of miscellaneous artifacts., undated (Box 329:155a, OS2)
      - Cosmic Egg, (...Brahm-Brahma)..."Basholi" style. Egg gold-leaft. For Charles, from [illegible], 1 photographic print; 9 1/2 x 15 3/4 cm (Box 329:155a)
    - Unidentified photograph by Diana Woelffer., ca. 1949. (Box OS3)
    - Photographs by Sam Rosenberg, Washington, D.C. (studies of plants and store fronts)., undated; 4prints. (Box 330:156)
      - by Sam Rosenberg- Washington, n.d.; 1 photographic print; 18 cm x 17 1/2 cm (Box 330:156)
      - by Sam Rosenberg, Washington, n.d.; 1 photographic print; 20 1/4 x 21 1/2 cm (Box 330:156)
      - by Sam Rosenberg, n.d.; 1 photographic print; 20 1/2 x 25 cm (Box 330:156)
    - Unidentified stage set or model. Print removed from Melville, Moby Dick (London: Constable, 1922), vol. 1, p. 210., undated (Box 330:157)
    - Color publicity photographs of the Beatles (George Harrison, John Lennon, Paul McCartney, and Ringo Starr)., undated; 4 prints. (Box 330:158)
    - Miscellaneous unidentified photographs., undated (Box 330:159-160)
  - H. Copy Prints Made For Publication (Not Owned by Charles Olson)
    - Original manuscript for "Journal of Swordfishing Cruise.", undated (Box 330:161)
      Olson: The Journal of Charles Olson Arhcives, Number 7 (Spring 1977): pages 36-37.
    - Original manuscript for "Added to making a Republic in gloom" (Maximus 584)., undated (Box 330:162)
      See A Guide to the Maximus Poems, plate 17.
    - Original manuscript for "The City Hall as is now was burned" with print reproducing the painting by Jerome Elwell. See Olson 1 (Spring 1974): 41, 49-53. 3 sets of prints., undated (Box 330:163-165)
    - Original manuscript for "The Secret of the Black Chrysanthemum." See Olson 3 (Spring 1975): 82-92. 2 sets of prints., undated (Box 330:166-167)
    - Original manuscript for poem beginning "there on the City's Front" (Maximus, p. 398). See Editing the Maximus Poems, Appendix 1, p. 1., undated (Box 330:168)
    - Original manuscript for poem beginning "I have been an ability" (Maximus, p. 495-499). See Editing the Maximus Poems, Appendix 1, p. 2-10., undated (Box 330:169)
    - Original manuscript for unpublished poem. See Editing the Maximus Poems, Appendix 1, p. 11., undated (Box 330:170)
    - Original manuscript for unpublished poem. See Editing the Maximus Poems, Appendix 1, p. 12., undated (Box 330:171)
    - Original manuscript for unpublished poem. See Editing the Maximus Poems, Appendix 1, p. 13., undated (Box 330:172)
    - Original manuscript for poem beginning "I was bold, I had courage" (Maximus, p. 612). See Editing the Maximus Poems, Appendix 1, p. 14., undated (Box 330:173)
    - Original manuscript for "Short Possible Poem" (Maximus, p. 618). See Editing the Maximus Poems, Appendix 1, p. 15-16., undated (Box 330:174)
    - Original manuscript for "my wife, my car" (Maximus, p. 635). 2 prints., undated (Box 330:175)
    - Original diagram for proposed reorganization of Black Mountain College, ca. 1954. See Olson 2 (Fall 1974): 49. 2 prints., undated (Box 330:175a)
    - Pages from Wolfshehl and von der Leyen's Alteste deutsche Dichtung with CO's notes. See A Guide to the Maximus Poems, plate 16., undated (Box 330:176)
    - Pages from The Trot-Moc Book of Indian Fairy Tales. See A Guide to the Maximus Poems, plate 4., undated (Box 330:177)
    - Pages from Carl Jung's Psychology and Alchemy, with CO's notes. See A Guide to the Maximus Poems, plate 18., undated (Box 330:178)
    - Samuel de Champlain's map of "Le Beauport" (Gloucester Harbor), with CO's notes. See Olson 5 (Spring 1976): 66., undated (Box 330:179)
    - Pages from Brooks Adams' The Law of Civilization and Decay, with CO's notes. See Olson 1 (Spring 1974): 59., undated (Box 330:179a)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts and annotations., undated (Box 331:180)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts and annotations. (Box 331:181)
    - Postcards from Robert Creeley to Charles Olson, ca. 6 October 1950. S, undated (Box 331:182)
      See Charles Olson Robert Creeley, v. 3, plates 3-5.
    - "Schooner Doris M. Hawes.", undated; With copy negative. (Box 331:183)
      Olson: The Journal of the Charles Olson Archives, Number 7 (Spring 1977): page 38.
    - "The Crew of the Auxiliary Schooner Doris M. Hawes Hoisting in Swordfish.", undated (Box 331:183a)
      Olson: The Journal of the Charles Olson Archhives, Number 7 (Spring 1977): page 5.
    - Drawings of Charles Olson, including one by Fielding Dawson., undated (Box 331:184)
      Olson: The Journal of the Charles Olson Archives, Number 8 (Fall 1977): page 63.
    - "Retiring Councillors Complimented," clipping from Gloucester Daily Times., undated; 2 prints. (Box 331:185)
      Olson: The Journal of the Charles Olson Archives, Number 5 (Spring 1976): page 67.
    - Cover of Fragmente 1 (1951)., undated (Box 331:186)
      See Charles Olson Robert Creeley, v. 7, plate 2.
    - Envelope of Robert Creeley's 11 Sept. 1951 letter to Charles Olson., undated (Box 331:187)
      See Charles Olson Robert Creeley, v. 7, plate 6.
    - Wellesley Hills Trolley., undated; Copy negative only. (Box 331:188)
      See The Post Office, p. 22.
    - Exhibition of Jargon Press books, including Maximus 1-10., undated; Copy print only. (Box 331:189)
      Photograph by Jonathan Williams. See Call Him Ishmael, plate 10.
    - Unidentified copy prints and miscellany., undated (Box 331:190-192)
    - Unsorted photographs., undated (Box 332-333)
    - Slides of Olson's rooms and portraits in Gloucester., undated (Box 334)
- Series VI: Black Mountain College Records
  - Board minutes. (Box 335)
  - Financial records, pensions, etc. (Box 336)
  - Financial records, pensions, etc. (Box 337)
  - Withholding tax records. (Box 338)
  - Business records, correspondence of rector., 1954-1956. (Box 339)
  - Business records: contingency salaries, etc. (Box 340)
  - Business records: miscellaneous., 1953-1956. (Box 341)
  - Business records: miscellaneous. (Box 342)
  - Business records: miscellaneous. (Box 343)
  - Sale of property. (Box 344)
  - Disposition of property. (Box 345)
  - Harriet Englehardt Collection of Latin American Textiles: correspondence and inventories. (Box 346)
  - Student files. Restricted for 75 years from date of file. (Box 347)
  - Student files. Restricted for 75 years from date of file. (Box 348)
  - Student transcripts. Restricted for 75 years from date of file. (Box 349)
  - Student report cards. Restricted for 75 years from date of file. (Box 350)
  - Published ephemera. (Box 351)
  - College Finances. (Box 352-353)
  - Instructor Records. (Box 354)
  - Microfilms of Black Mountain College Records. (Box 355-358)
- Series VII: Ephemera
  - Undated, 1928-1938. (Box 359)
  - 1939-1951. (Box 360)
  - 1952-1960. (Box 361)
  - 1960-1969. (Box 362)
  - Charles Olson's Typewriter. (Box 363)
  - Charles Olson's Pocket Litter. (Box 364)
  - American Book Awards Plaque, presented in Charles Olson in 1988 (post-mortem). (Box 365)
  - 2 Hand-tooled Leather Purses. (Box 366)
  - Charles Olson's Tarot Cards. (Box 367)
  - Charles Olson's Marbles and Pennywhistle. (Box 368)
- Series VIII: Related Materials
  - Anne Bosshard's Olson Materials. (Box 369)
  - Levi and Sarah Berman's Olson Materials. (Box 370)
  - Robert Creeley's Olson Materials. (Box 371-373)
  - Robert Duncan's Olson Materials. (Box 374)
  - Jeremy Prynne's Olson Materials. (Box 375)
  - B. Scott's Olson Materials. (Box 376)
  - Mary Shore's Olson Materials. (Box 377)
  - John Wiener's Olson Materials. (Box 378)
- Oversized Materials
  The oversized materials are part of their respective series and do not constitute a separate series in this collection.
  - Periodicals. (Box 379)
  - Literary Journals. (Box 380)
  - Newspapers. (Box 381)
  - Newspapers. (Box 382)
  - Artwork, Maps, MS, Correspondence. (Box 383)
  - Original Prints of Charles Olson's "This" in assorted colors from the Black Mountain Printshop. (Box 384)
  - Newspapers. (Box 385)
  - Letterbook. FRAGILE. (Box 386)
  - Artwork, Maps, MS, Correspondence. (Box 387)
  - Newspapers. (Box 388)
  - Maps. (Box 389)
  - Atlases and Newspapers. (Box 390)
  - Atlas. (Box 391)
  - Photographs. (Box 392)
  - Artwork and Maps. (Box 393)
  - MS and Correspondence. (Box 394)
  - Atlas. (Box 395)
  - Maps, Artwork, MS. (Box MC)
- Charles Olson reading, University of Kansas, n.d.; 1969-0001/R 15; Some static at the head in the background. Cross talk from previous recording detected at beginning of tape as well as middle of tape. This is not content from alternate tracks or imprint from previous winds. It is recorded on the same tracks as the poetry tracks. It appears as if this was content that was previously recorded on the tape and the erase head ahead of the record head didn't fully erase the previous content. Problem apparent through 07:25. The quality of the Charles Olson content is good. Content goes to end of tape. Single sided.; 1 sound tape reel (62 min.): analog, 3 3/4 ips, 2 channel, mono (Reel 1969-0001/R 15 P, Disk 1969-0001/CD 1 R)
  Scope and Content Note
  Includes readings of Maximus, to Gloucester; So Sassafras; Maximus, to Gloucester, Letter 27; An Ode on Cape Ann; From Maximus IV; "View": fr the Orontes; To travel Typhon; Chronicles; The Gulf of Maine; Maximus, from Dogtown - I; Going Right out of the Century; Maximus, to Gloucester Letter 15; A Later Note on Letter # 15; Letter # 41 [broken off]; Maximus, from Dogtown – II; The Distances; The Librarian; To Gerhardt, There, Among Europe's Things of Which He Has Written Us in His "Brief an Creeley und Olson"; In Cold Hell, in Thicket
  Access
  Original not available due to fragility. Use reference copy rather than the original.
- Charles Olson reading the Kingfishers and other poems for R.W. Emerson, August 19, 1950; 1969-0001/R 30; Quality is rather good. Occasionally can hear minor vibration/ motor noise in background - a fan? Motors outside? It's minimal. Single sided.; 1 sound tape reel (23 min.): analog, 3 3/4 ips, 2 channel, mono (Reel 1969-0001/R 30 P, Disk 1969-0001/CD 2 R)
- Charles Olson discusses Melville, Goddard College, April 14, 1962; 1969-0001/R 26; 1 sound tape reel (62 min.): analog, 3 3/4 ips, 2 channel, mono (Reel 1969-0001/R 26 P, Disk 1969-0001/CD 3 R)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Occasionally speaker sounds slightly muffled - possibly turning away from microphone? Because at the start of a new sentence he seems clear again. Content goes to end of tape but speaker finished in time - hear, "We just made it". Single sided.
- Charles Olson interviewed by Andrew Leinoff, part II, 1969; 1969-0001/R 19; 1 sound tape reel (64 min.): analog, 3 3/4 ips, 2 channel, mono (Disk 1969-0001/CD 4 R, Reel 1969-0001/R 19 P)
  Begins abruptly. Some rumblings in track - probably microphone movement and ambient sound in room. Ends abruptly, content goes to the end of the tape. Single Sided.
- Charles Olson interviewed by Andrew Leinoff, part I, 1969; 1969-0001/R 18; 1 sound tape reel (64 min.): analog, 3 3/4 ips, 2 channel, mono (Disk 1969-0001/CD 5 R, Reel 1969-0001/R 18 P)
  Lots of microphone noise when it is finally turned on. Some rumblings in track - probably microphone movement and ambient sound in room. Probably a single microphone shared between interviewer and interviewee. Ends abruptly, content goes to the end of the tape. Single Sided.
- Charles Olson reading, Goddard College, April 12, 1962; 1969-0001/R 2; 1 sound tape reel (60 min.): analog, 3 3/4 ips, 2 channel, mono (Reel 1969-0001/R 2 P, Disk 1969-0001/CD 6 R)
  Lots of rustling on the microphone at the start of the recording. Overall quality is good. Content goes to end of tape. Single sided.